# SERGIO E. GARCÍA-VERGARA

 $\boxtimes$  2232 Dunseath Ave NW, Apt 106  $\, \bullet \,$  Atlanta, GA 30318

☎ Cell: (787) 383 - 0475

e⊠ sergiodotgarcia@gmail.com • **Q**github.com/sgarciav

## **SUMMARY**

My area of expertise lies in the field of robotics, with more than 14 years of experience in algorithm development for autonomous robotic systems, collaborative systems, computer vision, software engineering, AI/ML, and human-robot interaction.

Over the last 5 years I have also gained invaluable experience building an early-stage deep tech startup from the ground up. As one of three co-founders and CTO, I've been responsible for advancing the startup's technology, fundraising, sales, and negotiating partnerships with industry leaders.

## **EDUCATION**

# Georgia Institute of Technology

Atlanta, GA

Ph.D. in Electrical and Computer Engineering

May 2017

Dissertation: Coupling of an Objective and Quantifiable Methodology for Assessing Upper-body Movements with VR Gaming Platforms

## Georgia Institute of Technology

Atlanta, GA

MS in Electrical and Computer Engineering

May 2014

Minor: Computer Science

# University of Puerto Rico at Mayagüez

Mayagüez, PR

BS in Electrical Engineering

June 2011

#### **SKILLS**

Programming Languages Python, C++, Node.js, Java, Matlab

Software Frameworks ROS & ROS 2, TensorFlow, PyTorch, YoloV11, CVAT, FiftyOne

Tools Docker, CMake, Git, Cygwin, Bash, LATEX, Emacs

Robotic Platforms MEAU RV-8CRL, UR3e/5e, UFactory xarm6,

ClearPath AMRs, DARwin-OP, DJI drones

Languages Fully proficient in English and Spanish. (Basic knowledge in German).

## WORK EXPERIENCE

#### CTO & Co-founder

October 2020 - present

RIF Robotics | Atlanta, GA

- Developing technology to automate the processing of surgical instruments in hospital sterile processing departments and off-site distribution centers to reduce errors and surgery delays, reduce the risk of patient infection, and increase throughput.
- Responsible for technical development, field deployment, fundraising, proposal writing, and customer interfacing.

## **Robotics Consultant**

July 2023 - June 2024

WDDLY Associates Corp. | Atlanta, GA

- Provided expert guidance in path planning and software development for the startup's UR3e robotic manipulator, aimed to automating the cutting of chickens.
- Successfully integrated the MoveIt motion planning framework for ROS 2 into the startup's autonomy architecture to generate robust and dynamic trajectories for their robotic manipulator.
- Successfully led the migration of WDDLY's autonomy architecture from ROS to ROS 2, enhancing system reliability, scalability, and compatibility with modern robotic frameworks.

#### **Robotics Consultant**

February 2021 - October 2022

Greenzie | Atlanta, GA

- Provided consulting services to the development team towards enhancing the autonomy architecture software of their autonomous lawnmowers.
- Tasks included: improved pipeline for obstacle detection and avoidance, improved navigation solutions, and research updating their autonomy architecture from ROS to ROS 2.

# Research Engineer II

January 2017 - October 2020

Georgia Tech Research Institute | Atlanta, GA

Supervisor: Dr. Charles Pippin

- Was project director and autonomy lead for a wide variety of DoD-sponsored projects. My team was constantly highly commended by the sponsors because of our problem solving skills and outstanding performance during demo days.
- Leveraged ROS to develop and implement algorithms for collaborative autonomous systems including, but not limited to, task allocation, path planning, and computer vision.
- Responsibilities included software and algorithm development, field testing autonomous systems, proposal creation, technical reporting, customer interfacing, and project management.

#### Graduate Research Assistant

May 2012 - December 2016

Georgia Tech HumAnS Lab | Atlanta, GA

Supervisor: Dr. Ayanna M. Howard

- As part of my PhD thesis, I implemented markerless motion tracking algorithms and developed an
  objective and quantifiable methodology to evaluate the kinematic performance of individuals who
  have some form of motor skills disorder.
- Developed a pattern recognition algorithm to enable the automatic adaptation of our system's settings as a function of the users' kinematic performance towards optimizing the user's physical therapy intervention protocol.

# DISSERTATION

S. García-Vergara, "Coupling of an objective and quantifiable methodology for assessing upper-body movements with virtual reality gaming platforms," Georgia Institute of Technology, 2017

Visit www.sergiogarciavergara.com/pages/publications for a full list of published works.

## **PATENTS**

### **Patents**

- 1. C. Farill, K. DeMarco, and S. García-Vergara, "Robotic end-effector with Secondary Gripper Mechanism", USPTO application number 63/592,191, October 22, 2023.
- 2. R.E. Torres-Muñiz, **S.E. García-Vergara**, B.A. Llorens-Bonilla, D. Sánchez-Cordero, and M. Lizama, "Switch-Actuated Joystick for Power Wheelchairs", U.S. Patent 8 622 166 B1, January 7, 2014.